<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Apache Beam</title>
    <description>Apache Beam is an open source, unified model and set of language-specific SDKs for defining and executing data processing workflows, and also data ingestion and integration flows, supporting Enterprise Integration Patterns (EIPs) and Domain Specific Languages (DSLs). Dataflow pipelines simplify the mechanics of large-scale batch and streaming data processing and can run on a number of runtimes like Apache Flink, Apache Spark, and Google Cloud Dataflow (a cloud service). Beam also brings DSL in different languages, allowing users to easily implement their data integration processes.
</description>
    <link>https://beam.apache.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://beam.apache.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Python SDK released in Apache Beam 0.6.0</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Apache Beam’s latest release, version &lt;a href=&quot;/get-started/downloads/&quot;&gt;0.6.0&lt;/a&gt;, introduces a new SDK – this time, for the Python programming language. The Python SDK joins the Java SDK as the second implementation of the Beam programming model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Python SDK incorporates all of the main concepts of the Beam model, including ParDo, GroupByKey, Windowing, and others. It features extensible IO APIs for writing bounded sources and sinks, and provides built-in implementation for reading and writing Text, Avro, and TensorFlow record files, as well as connectors to Google BigQuery and Google Cloud Datastore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two runners capable of executing pipelines written with the Python SDK today: &lt;a href=&quot;/documentation/runners/direct/&quot;&gt;Direct Runner&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/documentation/runners/dataflow/&quot;&gt;Dataflow Runner&lt;/a&gt;, both of which are currently limited to batch execution only. Upcoming features will shortly bring the benefits of the Python SDK to additional runners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;try-the-apache-beam-python-sdk&quot;&gt;Try the Apache Beam Python SDK&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to try out the Python SDK, a good place to start is the &lt;a href=&quot;/get-started/quickstart-py/&quot;&gt;Quickstart&lt;/a&gt;. After that, you can take a look at additional &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/apache/beam/tree/v0.6.0/sdks/python/apache_beam/examples&quot;&gt;examples&lt;/a&gt;, and deep dive into the &lt;a href=&quot;/documentation/sdks/pydoc/&quot;&gt;API reference&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at a quick example together. First, install the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;apache-beam&lt;/code&gt; package from PyPI and start your Python interpreter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pip install apache-beam
$ python
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will harness the power of Apache Beam to estimate Pi in honor of the recently passed Pi Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;import random
import apache_beam as beam

def run_trials(count):
  &quot;&quot;&quot;Throw darts into unit square and count how many fall into unit circle.&quot;&quot;&quot;
  inside = 0
  for _ in xrange(count):
    x, y = random.uniform(0, 1), random.uniform(0, 1)
    inside += 1 if x*x + y*y &amp;lt;= 1.0 else 0
  return count, inside

def combine_results(results):
  &quot;&quot;&quot;Given all the trial results, estimate pi.&quot;&quot;&quot;
  total, inside = sum(r[0] for r in results), sum(r[1] for r in results)
  return total, inside, 4 * float(inside) / total if total &amp;gt; 0 else 0

p = beam.Pipeline()
(p | beam.Create([500] * 10)  # Create 10 experiments with 500 samples each.
   | beam.Map(run_trials)     # Run experiments in parallel.
   | beam.CombineGlobally(combine_results)      # Combine the results.
   | beam.io.WriteToText('./pi_estimate.txt'))  # Write PI estimate to a file.

p.run()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This example estimates Pi by throwing random darts into the unit square and keeping track of the fraction of those darts that fell into the unit circle (see the full &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/apache/beam/blob/v0.6.0/sdks/python/apache_beam/examples/complete/estimate_pi.py&quot;&gt;example&lt;/a&gt; for details). If you are curious, you can check the result of our estimation by looking at the output file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ cat pi_estimate.txt*
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;roadmap&quot;&gt;Roadmap&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing on the Python SDK’s roadmap is to address two of its limitations. First, the existing runners are currently limited to bounded PCollections, and we are looking forward to extending the SDK to support unbounded PCollections (“streaming”). Additionally, we are working on extending support to more Apache Beam runners, and the upcoming Fn API will do the heavy lifting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these improvements will enable the Python SDK to fulfill the mission of Apache Beam: a unified programming model for batch and streaming data processing that can run on any execution engine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;join-us&quot;&gt;Join us!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please consider joining us, whether as a user or a contributor, as we work towards our first release with API stability. If you’d like to try out Apache Beam today, check out the latest &lt;a href=&quot;/get-started/downloads/&quot;&gt;0.6.0&lt;/a&gt; release. We welcome contributions and participation from anyone through our mailing lists, issue tracker, pull requests, and events.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 01:00:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://beam.apache.org/blog/2017/03/16/python-sdk-release.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://beam.apache.org/blog/2017/03/16/python-sdk-release.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Stateful processing with Apache Beam</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Beam lets you process unbounded, out-of-order, global-scale data with portable
high-level pipelines. Stateful processing is a new feature of the Beam model
that expands the capabilities of Beam, unlocking new use cases and new
efficiencies. In this post, I will guide you through stateful processing in
Beam: how it works, how it fits in with the other features of the Beam model,
what you might use it for, and what it looks like in code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning: new features ahead!&lt;/strong&gt;: This is a very new aspect of the Beam
model. Runners are still adding support. You can try it out today on multiple
runners, but do check the &lt;a href=&quot;/documentation/runners/capability-matrix/&quot;&gt;runner capability
matrix&lt;/a&gt; for
the current status in each runner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a quick recap: In Beam, a big data processing &lt;em&gt;pipeline&lt;/em&gt; is a directed,
acyclic graph of parallel operations called &lt;em&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PTransforms&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt; processing data
from &lt;em&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PCollections&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. I’ll expand on that by walking through this illustration:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;center-block&quot; src=&quot;/images/blog/stateful-processing/pipeline.png&quot; alt=&quot;A Beam Pipeline - PTransforms are boxes - PCollections are arrows&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boxes are &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PTransforms&lt;/code&gt; and the edges represent the data in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PCollections&lt;/code&gt;
flowing from one &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PTransform&lt;/code&gt; to the next. A &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PCollection&lt;/code&gt; may be &lt;em&gt;bounded&lt;/em&gt; (which
means it is finite and you know it) or &lt;em&gt;unbounded&lt;/em&gt; (which means you don’t know if
it is finite or not - basically, it is like an incoming stream of data that may
or may not ever terminate). The cylinders are the data sources and sinks at the
edges of your pipeline, such as bounded collections of log files or unbounded
data streaming over a Kafka topic. This blog post isn’t about sources or sinks,
but about what happens in between - your data processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two main building blocks for processing your data in Beam: &lt;em&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ParDo&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt;,
for performing an operation in parallel across all elements, and &lt;em&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;GroupByKey&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
(and the closely related &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CombinePerKey&lt;/code&gt; that I will talk about quite soon)
for aggregating elements to which you have assigned the same key. In the
picture below (featured in many of our presentations) the color indicates the
key of the element. Thus the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;GroupByKey&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CombinePerKey&lt;/code&gt; transform gathers all the
green squares to produce a single output element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;center-block&quot; src=&quot;/images/blog/stateful-processing/pardo-and-gbk.png&quot; alt=&quot;ParDo and GroupByKey/CombinePerKey:          Elementwise versus aggregating computations&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not all use cases are easily expressed as pipelines of simple &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ParDo&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Map&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;GroupByKey&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CombinePerKey&lt;/code&gt; transforms. The topic of this blog post is a new
extension to the Beam programming model: &lt;strong&gt;per-element operation augmented with
mutable state&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;center-block&quot; src=&quot;/images/blog/stateful-processing/stateful-pardo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stateful ParDo - sequential per-key processing with persistent state&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the illustration above, ParDo now has a bit of durable, consistent state on
the side, which can be read and written during the processing of each element.
The state is partitioned by key, so it is drawn as having disjoint sections for
each color. It is also partitioned per window, but I thought plaid 
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/stateful-processing/plaid.png&quot; alt=&quot;A plaid storage cylinder&quot; width=&quot;20&quot; /&gt; 
would be a bit much  :-). I’ll talk about
why state is partitioned this way a bit later, via my first example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the rest of this post, I will describe this new feature of Beam in detail -
how it works at a high level, how it differs from existing features, how to
make sure it is still massively scalable. After that introduction at the model
level, I’ll walk through a simple example of how you use it in the Beam Java
SDK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-does-stateful-processing-in-beam-work&quot;&gt;How does stateful processing in Beam work?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The processing logic of your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ParDo&lt;/code&gt; transform is expressed through the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt;
that it applies to each element.  Without stateful augmentations, a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt; is a
mostly-pure function from inputs to one or more outputs, corresponding to the
Mapper in a MapReduce.  With state, a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt; has the ability to access
persistent mutable state while processing each input element. Consider this
illustration:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;center-block&quot; src=&quot;/images/blog/stateful-processing/stateful-dofn.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stateful DoFn -          the runner controls input but the DoFn controls storage and output&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to note is that all the data - the little squares, circles, and
triangles - are red. This is to illustrate that stateful processing occurs in
the context of a single key - all of the elements are key-value pairs with the
same key. Calls from your chosen Beam runner to the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt; are colored in
yellow, while calls from the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt; to the runner are in purple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The runner invokes the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt;’s &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@ProcessElement&lt;/code&gt; method on each element for a
key+window.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt; reads and writes state - the curved arrows to/from the storage on
the side.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt; emits output (or side output) to the runner as usual via
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ProcessContext.output&lt;/code&gt; (resp. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ProcessContext.sideOutput&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this very high level, it is pretty intuitive: In your programming
experience, you have probably at some point written a loop over elements that
updates some mutable variables while performing other actions. The interesting
question is how does this fit into the Beam model: how does it relate with
other features? How does it scale, since state implies some synchronization?
When should it be used versus other features?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-does-stateful-processing-fit-into-the-beam-model&quot;&gt;How does stateful processing fit into the Beam model?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see where stateful processing fits in the Beam model, consider another
way that you can keep some “state” while processing many elements: CombineFn. In
Beam, you can write &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Combine.perKey(CombineFn)&lt;/code&gt; in Java or Python to apply an
associative, commutative accumulating operation across all the elements with a
common key (and window).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a diagram illustrating the basics of a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CombineFn&lt;/code&gt;, the simplest way
that a runner might invoke it on a per-key basis to build an accumulator and
extract an output from the final accumulator:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;center-block&quot; src=&quot;/images/blog/stateful-processing/combinefn.png&quot; alt=&quot;CombineFn - the runner controls input, storage, and output&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the illustration of stateful &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt;, all the data is colored red, since
this is the processing of Combine for a single key. The illustrated method
calls are colored yellow, since they are all controlled by the runner: The
runner invokes &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;addInput&lt;/code&gt; on each method to add it to the current accumulator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The runner persists the accumulator when it chooses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The runner calls &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;extractOutput&lt;/code&gt; when ready to emit an output element.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, the diagram for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CombineFn&lt;/code&gt; looks a whole lot like the diagram
for stateful &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt;. In practice, the flow of data is, indeed, quite similar.
But there are important differences, even so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The runner controls all invocations and storage here. You do not decide when
or how state is persisted, when an accumulator is discarded (based on
triggering) or when output is extracted from an accumulator.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can only have one piece of state - the accumulator. In a stateful DoFn
you can read only what you need to know and write only what has changed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You don’t have the extended features of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt;, such as multiple outputs per
input or side outputs. (These could be simulated by a sufficient complex
accumulator, but it would not be natural or efficient. Some other features of
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt; such as side inputs and access to the window make perfect sense for
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CombineFn&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the main thing that &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CombineFn&lt;/code&gt; allows a runner to do is to
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mergeAccumulators&lt;/code&gt;, the concrete expression of the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CombineFn&lt;/code&gt;’s associativity.
This unlocks some huge optimizations: the runner can invoke multiple instances
of a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CombineFn&lt;/code&gt; on a number of inputs and later combine them in a classic
divide-and-conquer architecture, as in this picture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;center-block&quot; src=&quot;/images/blog/stateful-processing/combiner-lifting.png&quot; alt=&quot;Divide-and-conquer aggregation with a CombineFn&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contract of a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CombineFn&lt;/code&gt; is that the result should be exactly the same,
whether or not the runner decides to actually do such a thing, or even more
complex trees with hot-key fanout, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This merge operation is not (necessarily) provided by a stateful &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt;: the
runner cannot freely branch its execution and recombine the states. Note that
the input elements are still received in an arbitrary order, so the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt; should
be insensitive to ordering and bundling but it doesn’t mean the output must be
exactly equal. (fun and easy fact: if the outputs are actually always equal,
then the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt; is an associative and commutative operator)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now you can see how a stateful &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt; differs from &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CombineFn&lt;/code&gt;, but I want to
step back and extrapolate this to a high level picture of how state in Beam
relates to using other features to achieve the same or similar goals: In a lot
of cases, what stateful processing represents is a chance to “get under the
hood” of the highly abstract mostly-deterministic functional paradigm of Beam
and do potentially-nondeterministic imperative-style programming that is hard
to express any other way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;example-arbitrary-but-consistent-index-assignment&quot;&gt;Example: arbitrary-but-consistent index assignment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose that you want to give an index to every incoming element for a
key-and-window. You don’t care what the indices are, just as long as they are
unique and consistent. Before diving into the code for how to do this in a Beam
SDK, I’ll go over this example from the level of the model. In pictures, you
want to write a transform that maps input to output like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;center-block&quot; src=&quot;/images/blog/stateful-processing/assign-indices.png&quot; alt=&quot;Assigning arbitrary but unique indices to each element&quot; width=&quot;180&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The order of the elements A, B, C, D, E is arbitrary, hence their assigned
indices are arbitrary, but downstream transforms just need to be OK with this.
There is no associativity or commutativity as far as the actual values are
concerned. The order-insensitivity of this transform only extends to the point
of ensuring the necessary properties of the output: no duplicated indices, no
gaps, and every element gets an index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conceptually expressing this as a stateful loop is as trivial as you can
imagine: The state you should store is the next index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As an element comes in, output it along with the next index.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increment the index.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This presents a good opportunity to talk about big data and parallelism,
because the algorithm in those bullet points is not parallelizable at all! If
you wanted to apply this logic over an entire &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PCollection&lt;/code&gt;, you would have to
process each element of the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PCollection&lt;/code&gt; one-at-a-time… this is obvious a
bad idea.  State in Beam is tightly scoped so that most of the time a stateful
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ParDo&lt;/code&gt; transform should still be possible for a runner to execute in parallel,
though you still have to be thoughtful about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A state cell in Beam is scoped to a key+window pair. When your DoFn reads or
writes state by the name of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;index&quot;&lt;/code&gt;, it is actually accessing a mutable cell
specified by &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;index&quot;&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;along with&lt;/em&gt; the key and window currently being
processed.  So, when thinking about a state cell, it may be helpful to consider
the full state of your transform as a table, where the rows are named according
to names you use in your program, like &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;index&quot;&lt;/code&gt;, and the columns are
key+window pairs, like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;table&quot;&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;(key, window)&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;(key, window)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;(key, window)&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;…&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;index&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;7&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;15&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;fizzOrBuzz?&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;fizz&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;7&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;fizzbuzz&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;…&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(if you have a superb spatial sense, feel free to imagine this as a cube where
keys and windows are independent dimensions)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can provide the opportunity for parallelism by making sure that table has
enough columns. You might have many keys and many windows, or you might have
many of just one or the other:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many keys in few windows, for example a globally windowed stateful computation
keyed by user ID.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many windows over few keys, for example a fixed windowed stateful computation
over a global key.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caveat: all Beam runners today parallelize only over the key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most often your mental model of state can be focused on only a single column of
the table, a single key+window pair. Cross-column interactions do not occur
directly, by design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;state-in-beams-java-sdk&quot;&gt;State in Beam’s Java SDK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I have talked a bit about stateful processing in the Beam model and
worked through an abstract example, I’d like to show you what it looks like to
write stateful processing code using Beam’s Java SDK.  Here is the code for a
stateful &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt; that assigns an arbitrary-but-consistent index to each element
on a per key-and-window basis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;MyKey&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;MyValue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;MyKey&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;MyValue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// A state cell holding a single Integer per key+window&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@StateId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;index&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;final&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;StateSpec&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Object&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ValueState&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;indexSpec&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; 
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;StateSpecs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;VarIntCoder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;());&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@ProcessElement&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;processElement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ProcessContext&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;context&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@StateId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;index&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ValueState&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;current&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;firstNonNull&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;read&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;context&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;current&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;context&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;element&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()));&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;current&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-py highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# State and timers are not yet supported in Beam's Python SDK.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Watch this space!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s dissect this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first thing to look at is the presence of a couple of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@StateId(&quot;index&quot;)&lt;/code&gt;
annotations. This calls out that you are using a mutable state cell named
“index” in this &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt;. The Beam Java SDK, and from there your chosen runner,
will also note these annotations and use them to wire up your DoFn correctly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@StateId(&quot;index&quot;)&lt;/code&gt; is annotated on a field of type &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;StateSpec&lt;/code&gt; (for
“state specification”). This declares and configures the state cell. The
type parameter &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ValueState&lt;/code&gt; describes the kind of state you can get out of this
cell - &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ValueState&lt;/code&gt; stores just a single value. Note that the spec itself is not
a usable state cell - you need the runner to provide that during pipeline
execution.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To fully specify a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ValueState&lt;/code&gt; cell, you need to provide the coder
that the runner will use (as necessary) to serialize the value
you will be storing. This is the invocation &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;StateSpecs.value(VarIntCoder.of())&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The second &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@StateId(&quot;index&quot;)&lt;/code&gt; annotation is on a parameter to your
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@ProcessElement&lt;/code&gt; method. This indicates access to the ValueState cell that
was specified earlier.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The state is accessed in the simplest way: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;read()&lt;/code&gt; to read it, and
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;write(newvalue)&lt;/code&gt; to write it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The other features of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt; are available in the usual way - such as
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;context.output(...)&lt;/code&gt;. You can also use side inputs, side outputs, gain access
to the window, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few notes on how the SDK and runners see this DoFn:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your state cells are all explicitly declared so a Beam SDK or runner can
reason about them, for example to clear them out when a window expires.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you declare a state cell and then use it with the wrong type, the Beam
Java SDK will catch that error for you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you declare two state cells with the same ID, the SDK will catch that,
too.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The runner knows that this is a stateful &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt; and may run it quite
differently, for example by additional data shuffling and synchronization in
order to avoid concurrent access to state cells.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at one more example of how to use this API, this time a bit more real-world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;example-anomaly-detection&quot;&gt;Example: anomaly detection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose you are feeding a stream of actions by your user into some complex
model to predict some quantitative expression of the sorts of actions they
take, for example to detect fraudulent activity. You will build up the model
from events, and also compare incoming events against the latest model to
determine if something has changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you try to express the building of your model as a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CombineFn&lt;/code&gt;, you may have
trouble with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mergeAccumulators&lt;/code&gt;. Assuming you could express that, it might
look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ModelFromEventsFn&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;extends&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;CombineFn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Event&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@Override&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;abstract&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;createAccumulator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;empty&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@Override&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;abstract&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;addInput&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;accumulator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Event&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;input&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;accumulator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;update&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;input&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// this is encouraged to mutate, for efficiency&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@Override&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;abstract&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;mergeAccumulators&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Iterable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;accumulators&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// ?? can you write this ??&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@Override&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;abstract&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;extractOutput&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;accumulator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;accumulator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-py highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# State and timers are not yet supported in Beam's Python SDK.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Watch this space!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you have a way to compute the model of a particular user for a window as
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Combine.perKey(new ModelFromEventsFn())&lt;/code&gt;. How would you apply this model to
the same stream of events from which it is calculated? A standard way to do
take the result of a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Combine&lt;/code&gt; transform and use it while processing the
elements of a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PCollection&lt;/code&gt; is to read it as a side input to a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ParDo&lt;/code&gt;
transform. So you could side input the model and check the stream of events
against it, outputting the prediction, like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PCollection&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;UserId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Event&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;events&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;final&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PCollectionView&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Map&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;UserId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;userModels&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;events&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Combine&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;perKey&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ModelFromEventsFn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;View&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;asMap&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;());&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PCollection&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;UserId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Prediction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;predictions&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;events&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ParDo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;UserId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Event&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;

      &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@ProcessElement&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;processElement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ProcessContext&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ctx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;UserId&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;userId&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ctx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;element&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getKey&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Event&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;event&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ctx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;element&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getValue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;model&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ctx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;sideinput&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;userModels&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;userId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Perhaps some logic around when to output a new prediction&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;…&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;userId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;prediction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;event&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;…&lt;/span&gt; 
      &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-py highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# State and timers are not yet supported in Beam's Python SDK.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Watch this space!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this pipeline, there is just one model emitted by the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Combine.perKey(...)&lt;/code&gt;
per user, per window, which is then prepared for side input by the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;View.asMap()&lt;/code&gt;
transform. The processing of the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ParDo&lt;/code&gt; over events will block until that side
input is ready, buffering events, and will then check each event against the
model. This is a high latency, high completeness solution: The model takes into
account all user behavior in the window, but there can be no output until the
window is complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose you want to get some results earlier, or don’t even have any
natural windowing, but just want continuous analysis with the “model so far”,
even though your model may not be as complete. How can you control the updates
to the model against which you are checking your events? Triggers are the
generic Beam feature for managing completeness versus latency tradeoffs. So here
is the same pipeline with an added trigger that outputs a new model one second
after input arrives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PCollection&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;UserId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Event&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;events&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PCollectionView&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Map&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;UserId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;userModels&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;events&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// A tradeoff between latency and cost&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Window&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;triggering&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;AfterProcessingTime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;pastFirstElementInPane&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;standardSeconds&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Combine&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;perKey&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ModelFromEventsFn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;View&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;asMap&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;());&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-py highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# State and timers are not yet supported in Beam's Python SDK.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Watch this space!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is often a pretty nice tradeoff between latency and cost: If a huge flood
of events comes in a second, then you will only emit one new model, so you
won’t be flooded with model outputs that you cannot even use before they are
obsolete. In practice, the new model may not be present on the side input
channel until many more seconds have passed, due to caches and processing
delays preparing the side input. Many events (maybe an entire batch of
activity) will have passed through the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ParDo&lt;/code&gt; and had their predictions
calculated according to the prior model. If the runner gave a tight enough
bound on cache expirations and you used a more aggressive trigger, you might be
able to improve latency at additional cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is another cost to consider: you are outputting many uninteresting
outputs from the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ParDo&lt;/code&gt; that will be processed downstream. If the
“interestingness” of the output is only well-defined relative to the prior
output, then you cannot use a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Filter&lt;/code&gt; transform to reduce data volume downstream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stateful processing lets you address both the latency problem of side inputs
and the cost problem of excessive uninteresting output. Here is the code, using
only features I have already introduced:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;UserId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Event&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;UserId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Prediction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@StateId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;model&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;final&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;StateSpec&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Object&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ValueState&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;modelSpec&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;StateSpecs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;coder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;());&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@StateId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;previousPrediction&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;final&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;StateSpec&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Object&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ValueState&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Prediction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;previousPredictionSpec&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;StateSpecs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Prediction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;coder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;());&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@ProcessElement&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;processElement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ProcessContext&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@StateId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;previousPrediction&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ValueState&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Prediction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;previousPredictionState&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@StateId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;model&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ValueState&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;modelState&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;UserId&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;userId&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;element&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getKey&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Event&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;event&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;element&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getValue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;model&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;modelState&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;read&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Prediction&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;previousPrediction&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;previousPredictionState&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;read&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Prediction&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;newPrediction&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;prediction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;event&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;add&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;event&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;modelState&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;model&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;previousPrediction&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;null&lt;/span&gt; 
        &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;||&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;shouldOutputNewPrediction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;previousPrediction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;newPrediction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;userId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;newPrediction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;previousPredictionState&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;write&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;newPrediction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-py highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# State and timers are not yet supported in Beam's Python SDK.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# Watch this space!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s walk through it,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You have two state cells declared, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@StateId(&quot;model&quot;)&lt;/code&gt; to hold the current
state of the model for a user and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@StateId(&quot;previousPrediction&quot;)&lt;/code&gt; to hold
the prediction output previously.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Access to the two state cells by annotation in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@ProcessElement&lt;/code&gt; method
is as before.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You read the current model via &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;modelState.read()&lt;/code&gt;. Because state is also
per-key-and-window, this is a model just for the UserId of the Event
currently being processed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You derive a new prediction &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;model.prediction(event)&lt;/code&gt; and compare it against
the last one you output, accessed via &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;previousPredicationState.read()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You then update the model &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;model.update()&lt;/code&gt; and write it via
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;modelState.write(...)&lt;/code&gt;. It is perfectly fine to mutate the value you pulled
out of state as long as you also remember to write the mutated value, in the
same way you are encouraged to mutate &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CombineFn&lt;/code&gt; accumulators.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the prediction has changed a significant amount since the last time you
output, you emit it via &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;context.output(...)&lt;/code&gt; and save the prediction using
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;previousPredictionState.write(...)&lt;/code&gt;. Here the decision is relative to the
prior prediction output, not the last one computed - realistically you might
have some complex conditions here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the above is just talking through Java! But before you go out and
convert all of your pipelines to use stateful processing, I want to go over
some considerations as to whether it is a good fit for your use case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;performance-considerations&quot;&gt;Performance considerations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To decide whether to use per-key-and-window state, you need to consider how it
executes. You can dig into how a particular runner manages state, but there are
some general things to keep in mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Partitioning per-key-and-window: perhaps the most important thing to
consider is that the runner may have to shuffle your data to colocate all
the data for a particular key+window. If the data is already shuffled
correctly, the runner may take advantage of this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Synchronization overhead: the API is designed so the runner takes care of
concurrency control, but this means that the runner cannot parallelize
processing of elements for a particular key+window even when it would otherwise
be advantageous.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Storage and fault tolerance of state: since state is per-key-and-window, the
more keys and windows you expect to process simultaneously, the more storage
you will incur. Because state benefits from all the fault tolerance /
consistency properties of your other data in Beam, it also adds to the cost of
committing the results of processing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expiration of state: also since state is per-window, the runner can reclaim
the resources when a window expires (when the watermark exceeds its allowed
lateness) but this could mean that the runner is tracking an additional timer
per key and window to cause reclamation code to execute.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;go-use-it&quot;&gt;Go use it!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are new to Beam, I hope you are now interested in seeing if Beam with
stateful processing addresses your use case.  If you are already using Beam, I
hope this new addition to the model unlocks new use cases for you.  Do check
the &lt;a href=&quot;/documentation/runners/capability-matrix/&quot;&gt;capability
matrix&lt;/a&gt; to
see the level of support for this new model feature on your favorite
backend(s).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And please do join the community at
&lt;a href=&quot;/get-started/support&quot;&gt;user@beam.apache.org&lt;/a&gt;. We’d love to
hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 00:00:01 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://beam.apache.org/blog/2017/02/13/stateful-processing.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://beam.apache.org/blog/2017/02/13/stateful-processing.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Media recap of the Apache Beam graduation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One year ago today Apache Beam was accepted into incubation at the Apache
Software Foundation. The community’s work over the past year culminated, just
over three weeks ago, with an &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2017/01/10/beam-graduates.html&quot;&gt;announcement&lt;/a&gt;
that Apache Beam has successfully graduated as a new Top-Level Project at the
foundation. Graduation sparked an additional interest in the project, from
corporate endorsements, news articles, interviews, to the volume of traffic to
our website and mailing lists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corporate endorsements include Google, PayPal, Talend, data Artisans, and
others. You can read more in the following blog posts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Google: “&lt;a href=&quot;https://opensource.googleblog.com/2017/01/apache-beam-graduates.html&quot;&gt;Apache Beam graduates to a top-level project&lt;/a&gt;” by Tyler Akidau.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Talend: “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.talend.com/blog/2017/01/13/future-apache-beam-now-top-level-apache-software-foundation-project/&quot;&gt;The Future of Apache Beam, Now a Top-Level Apache Software Foundation Project&lt;/a&gt;” by Jean-Baptiste Onofré.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Talend: “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.talend.com/blog/2017/01/23/apache-beam-way-greater-data-agility/?utm_medium=socialpost&amp;amp;utm_source=twitter&amp;amp;utm_campaign=blog&quot;&gt;Apache Beam Your Way to Greater Data Agility&lt;/a&gt;” by Shane Kent.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Google: “&lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/blog/big-data/2017/01/apache-beam-graduates-from-incubation-try-it-today-on-google-cloud-dataflow&quot;&gt;Apache Beam graduates from incubation: Try it today on Google Cloud Dataflow&lt;/a&gt;” by Frances Perry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;News coverage started with the Apache Software Foundation’s press release in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://globenewswire.com/news-release/2017/01/10/904692/0/en/The-Apache-Software-Foundation-Announces-Apache-Beam-as-a-Top-Level-Project.html&quot;&gt;Nasdaq GlobeNewswire&lt;/a&gt;,
and followed by coverage in many independent outlets. Some of those in English
include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ZDNet: “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zdnet.com/article/apache-beam-and-spark-new-coopetition-for-squashing-the-lambda-architecture/&quot;&gt;Apache Beam and Spark: New coopetition for squashing the Lambda Architecture?&lt;/a&gt;” by Tony Baer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Datanami: “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datanami.com/2017/01/10/google-lauds-outside-influence-apache-beam/&quot;&gt;Google Lauds Outside Influence on Apache Beam&lt;/a&gt;” by Alex Woodie.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;InfoWorld / JavaWorld: “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infoworld.com/article/3156598/big-data/apache-beam-unifies-batch-and-streaming-for-big-data.html&quot;&gt;Apache Beam unifies batch and streaming for big data&lt;/a&gt;” by Serdar Yegulalp, and republished in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.javaworld.com/article/3156598/big-data/apache-beam-unifies-batch-and-streaming-for-big-data.html&quot;&gt;JavaWorld&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JAXenter: “&lt;a href=&quot;https://jaxenter.com/apache-beam-interview-131314.html&quot;&gt;In a way, Apache Beam is the glue that connects many big data systems together&lt;/a&gt;” by Kypriani Sinaris.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;OStatic: “Apache Beam Unifies Batch and Streaming Data Processing” by Sam Dean. &lt;!-- http://ostatic.com/blog/apache-beam-unifies-batch-and-streaming-data-processing --&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enterprise Apps Today: “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.enterpriseappstoday.com/business-intelligence/data-analytics/apache-beam-graduates-to-help-define-streaming-data-processing.html&quot;&gt;Apache Beam Graduates to Help Define Streaming Data Processing&lt;/a&gt;” by Sean Michael Kerner.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Register: “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theregister.co.uk/2017/01/10/google_must_be_ibeamiing_as_apache_announces_its_new_top_level_projects/&quot;&gt;Google must be Beaming as Apache announces its new top-level projects&lt;/a&gt;” by Alexander J. Martin.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SiliconANGLE: “&lt;a href=&quot;http://siliconangle.com/blog/2017/01/11/apache-software-foundation-announces-2-top-level-projects/&quot;&gt;Apache Software Foundation announces two more top-level open source projects&lt;/a&gt;” by Mike Wheatley.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SD Times: “&lt;a href=&quot;http://sdtimes.com/apache-beam-goes-top-level/&quot;&gt;Apache Beam goes top level&lt;/a&gt;” by Alex Handy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graduation and media coverage helped push Beam website traffic to record levels.
The website traffic, measured in unique sessions per hour, peaked at more than
15 times above the previous week’s numbers. In a steady state, the traffic is
several times larger than before graduation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully these perspectives entice you to join us on this exciting ride, either
as a user or a contributor, as we work towards our first release with API
stability. If you’d like to try out Apache Beam today, check out the latest
&lt;a href=&quot;/get-started/downloads/&quot;&gt;0.4.0 release&lt;/a&gt;. We welcome
contribution and participation from anyone through our mailing lists, issue
tracker, pull requests, and events.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:01 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://beam.apache.org/blog/2017/02/01/graduation-media-recap.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://beam.apache.org/blog/2017/02/01/graduation-media-recap.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Apache Beam established as a new top-level project</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, the Apache Software Foundation &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.apache.org/foundation/entry/the-apache-software-foundation-announces&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt;
that Apache Beam has successfully graduated from incubation, becoming a new
Top-Level Project at the foundation and signifying that its “community and
products have been well-governed under the foundation’s meritocratic process
and principles”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graduation is an exciting milestone for Apache Beam. Becoming a top-level
project is a recognition of the amazing growth of the Apache Beam community,
both in terms of size and diversity. It is fantastic to see ever-increasing
participation on our development and user mailing lists, in pull requests,
and at conferences and meetups. Contributions of additional runners and IO
connectors further show the significant interest from other projects and
organizations in being part of our growing community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although graduation is a statement about community, our technical progress has
also been impressive. We started with code donations from several companies
that were tailored with a specific vendor and scenario in mind and had fragile
component boundaries. The whole community worked extremely hard over the past
year to refactor the codebase and documentation into a truly vendor-neutral and
extensible framework. We have established an impressive engineering system and
processes that promote test-driven development. This concerted focus on quality
and execution excellence enabled us to publish four releases, each significantly
better than the previous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going forward, we will continue to extend the core abstractions to distill
additional complex data processing patterns into intuitive APIs, and, at the
same time, enhance the ability to interconnect additional storage/messaging
systems and execution engines. Together, we are excited to push forward the
state of the art in distributed data processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also an opportunity to thank those who helped and supported us reaching
this milestone. None of this would be possible without the Apache Software
Foundation and its amazing volunteers who have wholeheartedly welcomed us into
the family. In particular, we’d like to thank the Apache Incubator community
for their guidance producing releases and following processes. We are especially
thankful to the Apache Infra team for their assistance establishing Beam’s
engineering system, particularly in the areas of testing infrastructure and
development productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On behalf of the whole Apache Beam community, thank you to our incubation
mentors Ted Dunning, Venkatesh Seetharam, and, previously, Bertrand Delacretaz
and Jim Jagielski, for teaching us the Apache Way and guiding us through
incubation. In particular, special thanks goes to our incubation champion and
mentor Jean-Baptiste Onofré, whose extraordinary help, day after day, was
instrumental in getting us here, and who continues as an active code contributor
and a member of the project management committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please consider joining us, whether as a user or a contributor, as we work
towards our first release with API stability. If you’d like to try out Apache
Beam today, check out the latest
&lt;a href=&quot;/get-started/downloads/&quot;&gt;0.4.0 release&lt;/a&gt;. We welcome
contribution and participation from anyone through our mailing lists, issue
tracker, pull requests, and events.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 00:00:01 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://beam.apache.org/blog/2017/01/10/beam-graduates.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://beam.apache.org/blog/2017/01/10/beam-graduates.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Release 0.4.0 adds a runner for Apache Apex</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The latest release 0.4.0 of &lt;a href=&quot;/&quot;&gt;Apache Beam&lt;/a&gt; adds a new runner for &lt;a href=&quot;http://apex.apache.org/&quot;&gt;Apache Apex&lt;/a&gt;. We are excited to reach this initial milestone and are looking forward to continued collaboration between the Beam and Apex communities to advance the runner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beam evolved from the Google Dataflow SDK and as incubator project has quickly adapted the Apache way, grown the community and attracts increasing interest from users that hope to benefit from a conceptual strong unified programming model that is portable between different big data processing frameworks (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oreilly.com/ideas/the-world-beyond-batch-streaming-101&quot;&gt;Streaming-101&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oreilly.com/ideas/the-world-beyond-batch-streaming-102&quot;&gt;Streaming-102&lt;/a&gt;). Multiple Apache projects already provide runners for Beam (see &lt;a href=&quot;/documentation/runners/capability-matrix/&quot;&gt;runners and capabilities matrix&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apex is a stream processing framework for low-latency, high-throughput, stateful and reliable processing of complex analytics pipelines on clusters. Apex was developed since 2012 and is used in production by large companies for real-time and batch processing at scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial revision of the runner was focussed on broad coverage of the Beam model on a functional level. That means, there will be follow up work in several areas to take the runner from functional to scalable and high performance to match the capabilities of Apex and its native API. The runner capabilities matrix shows that the Apex capabilities are well aligned with the Beam model. Specifically, the ability to track computational state in a fault tolerant and efficient manner is needed to broadly support the windowing concepts, including event time based processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stateful-stream-processor&quot;&gt;Stateful Stream Processor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apex was built as stateful stream processor from the ground up. Operators &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datatorrent.com/blog/blog-introduction-to-checkpoint/&quot;&gt;checkpoint&lt;/a&gt; state in a distributed and asynchronous manner that produces a consistent snapshot for the entire processing graph, which can be used for recovery. Apex also supports such recovery in an incremental, or fine grained, manner. This means only the portion of the DAG that is actually affected by a failure will be recovered while the remaining pipeline continues processing (this can be leveraged to implement use cases with special needs, such as speculative execution to achieve SLA on the processing latency). The state checkpointing along with idempotent processing guarantee is the basis for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datatorrent.com/blog/end-to-end-exactly-once-with-apache-apex/&quot;&gt;exactly-once results&lt;/a&gt; support in Apex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;translation-to-apex-dag&quot;&gt;Translation to Apex DAG&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Beam runner needs to implement the translation from the Beam model to the underlying frameworks execution model. In the case of Apex, the runner will translate the pipeline into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datatorrent.com/blog/tracing-dags-from-specification-to-execution/&quot;&gt;native (compositional, low level) DAG API&lt;/a&gt; (which is also the base for a number of other API that are available to specify applications that run on Apex). The DAG consists of operators (functional building blocks that are connected with streams. The runner provides the execution layer. In the case of Apex it is distributed stream processing, operators process data event by event. The minimum set of operators covers Beam’s primitive transforms: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ParDo.Bound&lt;/code&gt;,  &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ParDo.BoundMulti&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Read.Unbounded&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Read.Bounded&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;GroupByKey&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Flatten.FlattenPCollectionList&lt;/code&gt; etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;execution-and-testing&quot;&gt;Execution and Testing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this release, the Apex runner executes the pipelines in embedded mode, where, similar to the direct runner, everything is executed in a single JVM. See &lt;a href=&quot;/get-started/quickstart/&quot;&gt;quickstart&lt;/a&gt; on how to run the Beam examples with the Apex runner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embedded mode is useful for development and debugging. Apex in production runs distributed on Apache Hadoop YARN clusters. An example how a Beam pipeline can be embedded into an Apex application package to run on YARN can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tweise/apex-samples/tree/master/beam-apex-wordcount&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and support for direct launch in the runner is currently being worked on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Beam project has a strong focus on development process and tooling, including testing. For the runners, there is a comprehensive test suite with more than 200 integration tests that are executed against each runner to ensure they don’t break as changes are made. The tests cover the capabilities of the matrix and thus are a measure of completeness and correctness of the runner implementations. The suite was very helpful when developing the Apex runner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;outlook&quot;&gt;Outlook&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is to take the Apex runner from functional to ready for real applications that run distributed, leveraging the scalability and performance features of Apex, similar to its native API. This includes chaining of ParDos, partitioning, optimizing combine operations etc. To get involved, please see &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/issues/?jql=project%20%3D%20BEAM%20and%20component%20%3D%20runner-apex%20and%20resolution%20%3D%20unresolved&quot;&gt;JIRA&lt;/a&gt; and join the Beam community.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 09:00:01 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://beam.apache.org/blog/2017/01/09/added-apex-runner.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://beam.apache.org/blog/2017/01/09/added-apex-runner.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Testing Unbounded Pipelines in Apache Beam</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Beam Programming Model unifies writing pipelines for Batch and Streaming
pipelines. We’ve recently introduced a new PTransform to write tests for
pipelines that will be run over unbounded datasets and must handle out-of-order
and delayed data.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watermarks, Windows and Triggers form a core part of the Beam programming model
– they respectively determine how your data are grouped, when your input is
complete, and when to produce results. This is true for all pipelines,
regardless of if they are processing bounded or unbounded inputs. If you’re not
familiar with watermarks, windowing, and triggering in the Beam model,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oreilly.com/ideas/the-world-beyond-batch-streaming-101&quot;&gt;Streaming 101&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oreilly.com/ideas/the-world-beyond-batch-streaming-102&quot;&gt;Streaming 102&lt;/a&gt;
are an excellent place to get started. A key takeaway from
these articles: in realistic streaming scenarios with intermittent failures and
disconnected users, data can arrive out of order or be delayed. Beam’s
primitives provide a way for users to perform useful, powerful, and correct
computations in spite of these challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Beam pipeline authors, we need comprehensive tests that cover crucial
failure scenarios and corner cases to gain real confidence that a pipeline is
ready for production. The existing testing infrastructure within the Beam SDKs
permits tests to be written which examine the contents of a Pipeline at
execution time. However, writing unit tests for pipelines that may receive
late data or trigger multiple times has historically ranged from complex to
not possible, as pipelines that read from unbounded sources do not shut down
without external intervention, while pipelines that read from bounded sources
exclusively cannot test behavior with late data nor most speculative triggers.
Without additional tools, pipelines that use custom triggers and handle
out-of-order data could not be easily tested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog post introduces our new framework for writing tests for pipelines that
handle delayed and out-of-order data in the context of the LeaderBoard pipeline
from the Mobile Gaming example series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;leaderboard-and-the-mobile-gaming-example&quot;&gt;LeaderBoard and the Mobile Gaming Example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/apache/beam/blob/master/examples/java8/src/main/java/org/apache/beam/examples/complete/game/LeaderBoard.java#L177&quot;&gt;LeaderBoard&lt;/a&gt;
is part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/apache/beam/tree/master/examples/java8/src/main/java/org/apache/beam/examples/complete/game&quot;&gt;Beam mobile gaming examples&lt;/a&gt;
(and &lt;a href=&quot;/get-started/mobile-gaming-example/&quot;&gt;walkthroughs&lt;/a&gt;)
which produces a continuous accounting of user and team scores. User scores are
calculated over the lifetime of the program, while team scores are calculated
within fixed windows with a default duration of one hour. The LeaderBoard
pipeline produces speculative and late panes as appropriate, based on the
configured triggering and allowed lateness of the pipeline. The expected outputs
of the LeaderBoard pipeline vary depending on when elements arrive in relation
to the watermark and the progress of processing time, which could not previously
be controlled within a test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;writing-deterministic-tests-to-emulate-nondeterminism&quot;&gt;Writing Deterministic Tests to Emulate Nondeterminism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Beam testing infrastructure provides the
&lt;a href=&quot;/documentation/sdks/javadoc/2.0.0/org/apache/beam/sdk/testing/PAssert.html&quot;&gt;PAssert&lt;/a&gt;
methods, which assert properties about the contents of a PCollection from within
a pipeline. We have expanded this infrastructure to include
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/apache/beam/blob/master/sdks/java/core/src/main/java/org/apache/beam/sdk/testing/TestStream.java&quot;&gt;TestStream&lt;/a&gt;,
which is a PTransform that performs a series of events, consisting of adding
additional elements to a pipeline, advancing the watermark of the TestStream,
and advancing the pipeline processing time clock. TestStream permits tests which
observe the effects of triggers on the output a pipeline produces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While executing a pipeline that reads from a TestStream, the read waits for all
of the consequences of each event to complete before continuing on to the next
event, ensuring that when processing time advances, triggers that are based on
processing time fire as appropriate. With this transform, the effect of
triggering and allowed lateness can be observed on a pipeline, including
reactions to speculative and late panes and dropped data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;element-timings&quot;&gt;Element Timings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elements arrive either before, with, or after the watermark, which categorizes
them into the “early”, “on-time”, and “late” divisions. “Late” elements can be
further subdivided into “unobservably”, “observably”, and “droppably” late,
depending on the window to which they are assigned and the maximum allowed
lateness, as specified by the windowing strategy. Elements that arrive with
these timings are emitted into panes, which can be “EARLY”, “ON-TIME”, or
“LATE”, depending on the position of the watermark when the pane was emitted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using TestStream, we can write tests that demonstrate that speculative panes are
output after their trigger condition is met, that the advancing of the watermark
causes the on-time pane to be produced, and that late-arriving data produces
refinements when it arrives before the maximum allowed lateness, and is dropped
after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following examples demonstrate how you can use TestStream to provide a
sequence of events to the Pipeline, where the arrival of elements is interspersed
with updates to the watermark and the advance of processing time. Each of these
events runs to completion before additional events occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the diagrams, the time at which events occurred in “real” (event) time
progresses as the graph moves to the right. The time at which the pipeline
receives them progresses as the graph goes upwards. The watermark is represented
by the squiggly red line, and each starburst is the firing of a trigger and the
associated pane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;center-block&quot; src=&quot;/images/blog/test-stream/elements-all-on-time.png&quot; alt=&quot;Elements on the Event and Processing time axes, with the Watermark and produced panes&quot; width=&quot;442&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;everything-arrives-on-time&quot;&gt;Everything arrives on-time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if we create a TestStream where all the data arrives before the
watermark and provide the result PCollection as input to the CalculateTeamScores
PTransform:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TestStream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;infos&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TestStream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;create&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;AvroCoder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;addElements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;sky&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;blue&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Instant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0L&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)),&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;                &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;navy&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;blue&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Instant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0L&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)),&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;                &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;navy&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;blue&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Instant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0L&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;plus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;standardMinutes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))))&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Move the watermark past the end the end of the window&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;advanceWatermarkTo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Instant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0L&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;plus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TEAM_WINDOW_DURATION&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;                               &lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;plus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;standardMinutes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;advanceWatermarkToInfinity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PCollection&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;teamScores&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;createEvents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;CalculateTeamScores&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TEAM_WINDOW_DURATION&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ALLOWED_LATENESS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;we can then assert that the result PCollection contains elements that arrived:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;center-block&quot; src=&quot;/images/blog/test-stream/elements-all-on-time.png&quot; alt=&quot;Elements all arrive before the watermark, and are produced in the on-time pane&quot; width=&quot;442&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Only one value is emitted for the blue team&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PAssert&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;that&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;teamScores&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;inWindow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;window&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;containsInAnyOrder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;blue&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;run&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-elements-are-late-but-arrive-before-the-end-of-the-window&quot;&gt;Some elements are late, but arrive before the end of the window&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also add data to the TestStream after the watermark, but before the end
of the window (shown below to the left of the red watermark), which demonstrates
“unobservably late” data - that is, data that arrives late, but is promoted by
the system to be on time, as it arrives before the watermark passes the end of
the window&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TestStream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;infos&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TestStream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;create&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;AvroCoder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;addElements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;sky&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;blue&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Instant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0L&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)),&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;       &lt;/span&gt;         &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;navy&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;blue&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Instant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0L&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;plus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;standardMinutes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))))&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Move the watermark up to &quot;near&quot; the end of the window&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;advanceWatermarkTo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Instant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0L&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;plus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TEAM_WINDOW_DURATION&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;               &lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;                &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;minus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;standardMinutes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;addElements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;sky&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;blue&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;ZERO&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;advanceWatermarkToInfinity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PCollection&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;teamScores&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;createEvents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;CalculateTeamScores&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TEAM_WINDOW_DURATION&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ALLOWED_LATENESS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;center-block&quot; src=&quot;/images/blog/test-stream/elements-unobservably-late.png&quot; alt=&quot;An element arrives late, but before the watermark passes the end of the window, and is produced in the on-time pane&quot; width=&quot;442&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Only one value is emitted for the blue team&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PAssert&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;that&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;teamScores&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;inWindow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;window&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;containsInAnyOrder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;blue&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;run&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elements-are-late-and-arrive-after-the-end-of-the-window&quot;&gt;Elements are late, and arrive after the end of the window&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By advancing the watermark farther in time before adding the late data, we can
demonstrate the triggering behavior that causes the system to emit an on-time
pane, and then after the late data arrives, a pane that refines the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TestStream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;infos&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TestStream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;create&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;AvroCoder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;addElements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;sky&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;blue&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Instant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0L&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)),&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;          &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;navy&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;blue&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Instant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0L&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;plus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;standardMinutes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Move the watermark up to &quot;near&quot; the end of the window&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;advanceWatermarkTo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Instant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0L&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;plus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TEAM_WINDOW_DURATION&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;                                &lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;minus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;standardMinutes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;addElements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;sky&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;blue&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;ZERO&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;advanceWatermarkToInfinity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PCollection&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;teamScores&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;createEvents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;CalculateTeamScores&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TEAM_WINDOW_DURATION&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ALLOWED_LATENESS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;center-block&quot; src=&quot;/images/blog/test-stream/elements-observably-late.png&quot; alt=&quot;Elements all arrive before the watermark, and are produced in the on-time pane&quot; width=&quot;442&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// An on-time pane is emitted with the events that arrived before the window closed&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PAssert&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;that&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;teamScores&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;inOnTimePane&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;window&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;containsInAnyOrder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;blue&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// The final pane contains the late refinement&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PAssert&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;that&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;teamScores&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;inFinalPane&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;window&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;containsInAnyOrder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;blue&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;run&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elements-are-late-and-after-the-end-of-the-window-plus-the-allowed-lateness&quot;&gt;Elements are late, and after the end of the window plus the allowed lateness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we push the watermark even further into the future, beyond the maximum
configured allowed lateness, we can demonstrate that the late element is dropped
by the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TestStream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;infos&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TestStream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;create&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;AvroCoder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;addElements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;sky&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;blue&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;ZERO&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;         &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;navy&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;blue&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;standardMinutes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Move the watermark up to &quot;near&quot; the end of the window&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;advanceWatermarkTo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Instant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;plus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TEAM_WINDOW_DURATION&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;                                        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;plus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ALLOWED_LATENESS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;                                        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;plus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;standardMinutes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;addElements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;                     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;sky&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;                     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;blue&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;                     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;                     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Instant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;plus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TEAM_WINDOW_DURATION&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;minus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;standardMinutes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;advanceWatermarkToInfinity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PCollection&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;teamScores&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;createEvents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;CalculateTeamScores&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TEAM_WINDOW_DURATION&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ALLOWED_LATENESS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;center-block&quot; src=&quot;/images/blog/test-stream/elements-droppably-late.png&quot; alt=&quot;Elements all arrive before the watermark, and are produced in the on-time pane&quot; width=&quot;442&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// An on-time pane is emitted with the events that arrived before the window closed&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PAssert&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;that&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;teamScores&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;inWindow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;window&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;containsInAnyOrder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;blue&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;run&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elements-arrive-before-the-end-of-the-window-and-some-processing-time-passes&quot;&gt;Elements arrive before the end of the window, and some processing time passes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using additional methods, we can demonstrate the behavior of speculative
triggers by advancing the processing time of the TestStream. If we add elements
to an input PCollection, occasionally advancing the processing time clock, and
apply &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CalculateUserScores&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TestStream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;create&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;AvroCoder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;addElements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;scarlet&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;red&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Instant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0L&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)),&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;              &lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;scarlet&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;red&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Instant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0L&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;plus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;standardMinutes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;advanceProcessingTime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;standardMinutes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;addElements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;oxblood&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;red&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Instant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0L&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;plus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;standardSeconds&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;22&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)),&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;              &lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GameActionInfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;scarlet&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;red&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Instant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0L&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;plus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;standardMinutes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;advanceProcessingTime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Duration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;standardMinutes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;advanceWatermarkToInfinity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PCollection&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Integer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;userScores&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;infos&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;apply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;CalculateUserScores&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ALLOWED_LATENESS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;center-block&quot; src=&quot;/images/blog/test-stream/elements-processing-speculative.png&quot; alt=&quot;Elements all arrive before the watermark, and are produced in the on-time pane&quot; width=&quot;442&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-java highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PAssert&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;that&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;userScores&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;inEarlyGlobalWindowPanes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;containsInAnyOrder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;scarlet&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;                        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;scarlet&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;9&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
                           &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;KV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;oxblood&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;run&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;teststream---under-the-hood&quot;&gt;TestStream - Under the Hood&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TestStream relies on a pipeline concept we’ve introduced, called quiescence, to
utilize the existing runner infrastructure while providing guarantees about when
a root transform will called by the runner. This consists of properties about
pending elements and triggers, namely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No trigger is permitted to fire but has not fired&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All elements are either buffered in state or cannot progress until a side input becomes available&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simplified, this means that, in the absence of an advancement in input
watermarks or processing time, or additional elements being added to the
pipeline, the pipeline will not make progress. Whenever the TestStream PTransform
performs an action, the runner must not reinvoke the same instance until the
pipeline has quiesced. This ensures that the events specified by TestStream
happen “in-order”, which ensures that input watermarks and the system clock do
not advance ahead of the elements they hoped to hold up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DirectRunner has been modified to use quiescence as the signal that it
should add more work to the Pipeline, and the implementation of TestStream in
that runner uses this fact to perform a single output per event. The DirectRunner
implementation also directly controls the runner’s system clock, ensuring that
tests will complete promptly even if there is a multi-minute processing time
trigger located within the pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TestStream transform is supported in the DirectRunner. For most users, tests
written using TestPipeline and PAsserts will automatically function while using
TestStream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The addition of TestStream alongside window and pane-specific matchers in PAssert
has enabled the testing of Pipelines which produce speculative and late panes.
This permits tests for all styles of pipeline to be expressed directly within the
Java SDK. If you have questions or comments, we’d love to hear them on the
&lt;a href=&quot;/get-started/support/&quot;&gt;mailing lists&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2016 11:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://beam.apache.org/blog/2016/10/20/test-stream.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://beam.apache.org/blog/2016/10/20/test-stream.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Strata+Hadoop World and Beam</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Tyler Akidau and I gave a &lt;a href=&quot;http://conferences.oreilly.com/strata/hadoop-big-data-ny/public/schedule/detail/52129&quot;&gt;three-hour tutorial&lt;/a&gt; on Apache Beam at Strata+Hadoop World 2016. We had a plethora of help from our TAs: Kenn Knowles, Reuven Lax, Felipe Hoffa, Slava Chernyak, and Jamie Grier. There were a total of 66 people that attended the session.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/IMG_20160927_170956.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Exercise time&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to take a look at the tutorial materials, we’ve put them up &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/eljefe6a/beamexample&quot;&gt;on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. This includes the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/eljefe6a/beamexample/blob/master/BeamTutorial/slides.pdf&quot;&gt;actual slides&lt;/a&gt; as well as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/eljefe6a/beamexample/tree/master/BeamTutorial/src/main/java/org/apache/beam/examples/tutorial/game&quot;&gt;exercises&lt;/a&gt; that we covered. If you’re looking to learn a little about Beam, this is a good way to start. The exercises are based on an imaginary mobile game where data needs processing and are based on code in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/apache/beam/tree/master/examples/java8/src/main/java/org/apache/beam/examples/complete/game&quot;&gt;Beam examples directory&lt;/a&gt;. The code has TODOs for where you need to fill in code or there are full sample solutions to look over our code. You can run these examples on your own machine or on a cluster using a runner that Beam supports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to share some of takeaways I had about Beam during the conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Data Engineers are looking to Beam as a way to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oreilly.com/ideas/future-proof-and-scale-proof-your-code&quot;&gt;future-proof&lt;/a&gt;, meaning that code is portable between the various Big Data frameworks. In fact, many of the attendees were still on Hadoop MapReduce and looking to transition to a new framework. They’re realizing that continually rewriting code isn’t the most productive approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data Scientists are really interested in using Beam. They interested in having a single API for doing analysis instead of several different APIs. We talked about Beam’s progress on the Python API. If you want to take a peek, it’s being actively developed on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/apache/beam/tree/master/sdks/python&quot;&gt;feature branch&lt;/a&gt;. As Beam matures, we’re looking to add other supported languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We heard &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jessetanderson/status/781124173108305920&quot;&gt;loud and clear&lt;/a&gt; from Beam users that great runner support is crucial to adoption. We have great Apache Flink support. During the conference we had some more volunteers offer their help on the Spark runner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On management and thought leader side, Beam went from “what’s Beam?” at previous conferences to “I’m interested in Beam.” or “I’ve formed an informed opinion on Beam.” at this conference. This is one of the metrics I look for in early technology adoption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/IMG_20160927_170455.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;So much brainpower answering questions&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We rounded out the tutorial with live demonstrations of Beam running on Apache Spark, Apache Flink, the local runner, and DataFlow runner. Then, we brought in the big brainpower and had a Q and A session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re attending a conference, we encourage you to look for a Beam session. If you want to use these materials to give your own Beam talk or tutorial, we’re happy to help you. In addition to this tutorial, we have &lt;a href=&quot;/contribute/presentation-materials/&quot;&gt;other presentation materials&lt;/a&gt;. You can reach out to us on the &lt;a href=&quot;/get-started/support/&quot;&gt;user mailing list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 10:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://beam.apache.org/beam/update/2016/10/11/strata-hadoop-world-and-beam.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://beam.apache.org/beam/update/2016/10/11/strata-hadoop-world-and-beam.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>beam</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Apache Beam: Six Months in Incubation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been just over six months since Apache Beam was formally accepted into incubation with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apache.org&quot;&gt;Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;. As a community, we’ve been hard at work getting Beam off the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking just at raw numbers for those first six months, that’s:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;48,238 lines of preexisting code donated by Cloudera, dataArtisans, and Google.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;761 pull requests from 45 contributors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;498 Jira issues opened and 245 resolved.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 incubating release (and another 1 in progress).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4,200 hours of automated tests.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;161 subscribers / 606 messages on user@.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;217 subscribers / 1205 messages on dev@.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;277 stars and 174 forks on GitHub.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And behind those numbers, there’s been a ton of technical progress, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Refactoring of the entire codebase, examples, and tests to be truly runner-independent.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New functionality in the Apache Flink runner for timestamps/windows in batch and bounded sources and side inputs in streaming mode.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work in progress to upgrade the Apache Spark runner to use Spark 2.0.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Several new runners from the wider Apache community – Apache Gearpump has its own feature branch, Apache Apex has a PR, and conversations are starting on Apache Storm and others.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New SDKs/DSLs for exposing the Beam model – the Python SDK from Google is in on a feature branch, and there are plans to add the Scio DSL from Spotify.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for additional data sources and sinks – Apache Kafka and JMS are in, there are PRs for Amazon Kinesis, Apache Cassandra, and MongoDB, and more connectors are being planned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps most importantly, we’re committed to building an involved, welcoming community. So far, we’ve:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Started building a vibrant developer community, with detailed design discussions on features like DoFn reuse semantics, serialization technology, and an API for accessing state.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Started building a user community with an active mailing list and improvements to the website and documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Had multiple talks on Beam at venues including ApacheCon, Hadoop Summit, Kafka Summit, JBCN Barcelona, and Strata.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Presented at multiple existing meetups and are starting to organize some of our own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it’s nice to reflect back on all we’ve done, we’re working full &lt;em&gt;stream&lt;/em&gt; ahead towards a stable release and graduation from incubator. And we’d love your help – join the &lt;a href=&quot;/get-started/support/&quot;&gt;mailing lists&lt;/a&gt;, check out the &lt;a href=&quot;/contribute/contribution-guide/&quot;&gt;contribution guide&lt;/a&gt;, and grab a &lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/BEAM-520?jql=project%20%3D%20BEAM%20AND%20resolution%20%3D%20Unresolved%20AND%20labels%20in%20(newbie%2C%20starter)&quot;&gt;starter task&lt;/a&gt; from Jira!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 00:00:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://beam.apache.org/blog/2016/08/03/six-months.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://beam.apache.org/blog/2016/08/03/six-months.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The first release of Apache Beam!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m happy to announce that Apache Beam has officially released its first
version – 0.1.0-incubating. This is an exciting milestone for the project,
which joined the Apache Software Foundation and the Apache Incubator earlier
this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This release publishes the first set of Apache Beam binaries and source code,
making them readily available for our users. The initial release includes the
SDK for Java, along with three runners: Apache Flink, Apache Spark and Google
Cloud Dataflow, a fully-managed cloud service. The release is available both
in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://search.maven.org/#search%7Cga%7C1%7Cg%3A%22org.apache.beam%22&quot;&gt;Maven Central Repository&lt;/a&gt;,
as well as a download from the &lt;a href=&quot;/get-started/downloads/&quot;&gt;project’s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this release was process-oriented. In particular, the Beam
community wanted to release existing functionality to our users, build and
validate the release processes, and obtain validation from the Apache Software
Foundation and the Apache Incubator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to encourage everyone to try out this release. Please keep in mind
that this is the first incubating release – significant changes are to be
expected. As we march toward stability, a rapid cadence of future releases is
anticipated, perhaps one every 1-2 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, the Beam community welcomes feedback. Stabilization, usability and
the developer experience will be our focus for the next several months. If you
have any comments or discover any issues, I’d like to invite you to reach out
to us via &lt;a href=&quot;/get-started/support/&quot;&gt;user’s mailing list&lt;/a&gt; or the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/BEAM/&quot;&gt;Apache JIRA issue tracker&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2016 00:00:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://beam.apache.org/beam/release/2016/06/15/first-release.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://beam.apache.org/beam/release/2016/06/15/first-release.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>beam</category>
        
        <category>release</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How We Added Windowing to the Apache Flink Batch Runner</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We recently achieved a major milestone by adding support for windowing to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://flink.apache.org&quot;&gt;Apache Flink&lt;/a&gt; Batch runner. In this post we would like to explain what this means for users of Apache Beam and highlight some of the implementation details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we start, though, let’s quickly talk about the execution of Beam programs and how this is relevant to today’s post. A Beam pipeline can contain bounded and unbounded sources. If the pipeline only contains bounded sources it can be executed in a batch fashion, if it contains some unbounded sources it must be executed in a streaming fashion. When executing a Beam pipeline on Flink, you don’t have to choose the execution mode. Internally, the Flink runner either translates the pipeline to a Flink &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DataSet&lt;/code&gt; program or a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DataStream&lt;/code&gt; program, depending on whether unbounded sources are used in the pipeline. In the following, when we say “Batch runner” what we are really talking about is the Flink runner being in batch execution mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-does-this-mean-for-users&quot;&gt;What does this mean for users?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Support for windowing was the last missing puzzle piece for making the Flink Batch runner compatible with the Beam model. With the latest change to the Batch runner users can now run any pipeline that only contains bounded sources and be certain that the results match those of the original reference-implementation runners that were provided by Google as part of the initial code drop coming from the Google Dataflow SDK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious part of the change is that windows can now be assigned to elements and that the runner respects these windows for the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;GroupByKey&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Combine&lt;/code&gt; operations. A not-so-obvious change concerns side-inputs. In the Beam model, side inputs respect windows; when a value of the main input is being processed only the side input that corresponds to the correct window is available to the processing function, the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DoFn&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting side-input semantics right is an important milestone in it’s own because it allows to use a big suite of unit tests for verifying the correctness of a runner implementation. These tests exercise every obscure detail of the Beam programming model and verify that the results produced by a runner match what you would expect from a correct implementation. In the suite, side inputs are used to compare the expected result to the actual result. With these tests being executed regularly we can now be more confident that the implementation produces correct results for user-specified pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;under-the-hood&quot;&gt;Under the Hood&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basis for the changes is the introduction of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;WindowedValue&lt;/code&gt; in the generated Flink transformations. Before, a Beam &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PCollection&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; would be transformed to a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DataSet&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. Now, we instead create a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DataSet&amp;lt;WindowedValue&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;WindowedValue&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; stores meta data about the value, such as the timestamp and the windows to which it was assigned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this basic change out of the way we just had to make sure that windows were respected for side inputs and that &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Combine&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;GroupByKey&lt;/code&gt; correctly handled windows. The tricky part there is the handling of merging windows such as session windows. For these we essentially emulate the behavior of a merging &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;WindowFn&lt;/code&gt; in our own code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we got side inputs working we could enable the aforementioned suite of tests to check how well the runner behaves with respect to the Beam model. As can be expected there were quite some discrepancies but we managed to resolve them all. In the process, we also slimmed down the runner implementation. For example, we removed all custom translations for sources and sinks and are now relying only on Beam code for these, thereby greatly reducing the maintenance overhead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We reached a major milestone in adding windowing support to the Flink Batch runner, thereby making it compatible with the Beam model. Because of the large suite of tests that can now be executed on the runner we are also confident about the correctness of the implementation and about it staying that way in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2016 09:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://beam.apache.org/blog/2016/06/13/flink-batch-runner-milestone.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://beam.apache.org/blog/2016/06/13/flink-batch-runner-milestone.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
